PRIVATE INVESTIGATION AGENCY
AGENCJA DETEKTYWISTYCZNA
As for the P.I. himself…
Zajmę się tym detektywem.
What about the human with the parasite in his arm?
A człowiek z pasożytem w ręce?
Miki's supposed to go tomorrow.
Miki uda się do niego jutro.
Youko! Yumi!
Youko! Yumi!
AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
HAPPY FAMILY
SZCZĘŚLIWA RODZINKA
You know what I think?
Wiesz, co myślę?
Your combat style must be unique.
Masz unikalny styl walki.
That's why others of my kind were done in so easily.
Dlatego tak łatwo poradziłeś sobie z resztą.
It's hard to comprehend that
Trudno uwierzyć, że jesteś silniejszy,
even with the human brain intact, you're actually stronger.
choć twój ludzki mózg pozostał niezmieniony.
Based on our analysis of the body in our dining area,
Jednak przyglądając się ciału w miejscu żeru,
it doesn't seem like victory was immediate, either.
zobaczyliśmy, że nie wygrałeś tam tak szybko.
Oh, I guess it wasn't the right moment to laugh.
To nie był stosowny moment do śmiechu.
So, how do you usually do it?
Jak to zwykle robisz?
Can you tell me how you fight?
Powiesz mi, jak walczysz?
What's with him?
Co z nim?
He talks up a storm and he's creepy as hell.
Jest strasznie rozgadany.
Stay on guard. I'm sure he's trying to get a feel for us.
Bądź czujny. Próbuje nas wyczuć.
No matter how expressive he may seem,
Choć wydaje się ekspresywny,
keep in mind that it is totally alien from human emotions.
ludzkie emocje są mu całkowicie obce.
I see.
Rozumiem.
You always confer while you fight.
Porozumiewacie się w trakcie walki.
Is that effective?
To efektywne?
You have excellent speed and motion detection.
Znakomita prędkość i refleks.
I think it'll be a bit difficult to bring your body back intact.
Raczej nie uda mi się sprowadzić twojego ciała w całości.
There are too many blades.
Za dużo ostrzy.
Why not produce more of your own?
To sam zrób ich więcej.
It's not that simple.
To nie takie proste.
They have to be of a certain size at minimum.
Muszą mieć odpowiednie rozmiary.
He's pretty slow.
Jest powolny.
You might be faster than him,
Może i jesteś szybszy,
but it's not as if you have a lot of stamina.
ale nie masz dobrej kondycji.
Right.
Racja.
I've been running all day.
Biegałem cały dzień.
I think we're in deep trouble.
Niedobrze.
I am also exhausted. The fight was short but intense.
Też jestem wykończony. Walka była krótka, ale intensywna.
So we're a tired duo.
Więc obaj jesteśmy zmęczeni.
But we've managed to put some distance between us and him.
Ale udało się nam nieco oddalić.
He's a new type of enemy, three on one body.
To nowy rodzaj przeciwnika. Trójka w jednym ciele.
What about his legs?
A jego nogi?
His legs?
Nogi?
You said during the last fight that the human part is their weakness.
Mówiłeś, że ich słaby punkt to ludzkie ciało.
If we can manage to strike his legs…
Jeśli trafimy go w nogi…
What? Is it not possible?
Co? To niemożliwe?
It bothers me
Nie potrafię wyczuć, w których miejscach znajdują się pasożyty.
Why not? There are three of them.
Czemu? Jest ich trójka.
It has to be the head and both arms.
Muszą być w głowie i rękach.
It should be, but somehow…
Tak powinno być, ale…
We messed up. He's caught up to us.
O nie, dogonił nas.
He tripped again.
Znów się przewrócił.
"Again"?
Znów?
Man, you really like to run.
Ty naprawdę lubisz uciekać.
This is getting really tiresome.
To się robi męczące.
Let's just forget about leaving bodies intact.
Twoje ciało nie skończy w jednym kawałku.
We don't have a choice. We'll have to gamble.
Musimy zaryzykować.
Let's aim for the legs, as you suggested.
Celujmy w jego nogi.
I'll block the next attack that comes from the right.
Zablokuję atak z prawej.
You'll have to dodge the attack coming from the left
A ty zrób unik przed atakiem z lewej, ale stój w miejscu.
You're asking the impossible.
To niemożliwe.
Impossible.
Niemożliwe.
I win!
Wygrałem!
What?
Co?
-What was that? -A mid-air collision.
- Co to było? - Zaplątały mu się macki.
I'm getting a clearer picture of his true nature now.
Zaczynam rozumieć, jak jest zbudowany.
True nature?
Naprawdę?
Yes.
Tak.
I was certainly taken aback at first,
Początkowo byłem zdezorientowany,
but it may be more for show than anything else.
ale on robi sporo tylko na pokaz.
I hope so.
Miejmy nadzieję.
First, the parasites encompass an area greater than his head and two arms.
Pasożyty nie zajmują tylko głowy i rąk.
The leg I managed to attack earlier wasn't human.
Noga, którą zaatakowałem, też nie była ludzka.
No way!
Niemożliwe!
In any case, I am certain that the head is still the control center.
Jestem pewien, że jego głowa jest centrum kontroli.
I don't sense independent thought in his arms' movements.
Nie wyczuwam niezależnych myśli w jego ramionach.
Here he comes.
Idzie.
I don't care how many times I have to run!
Mogę uciekać w nieskończoność.
I found a good location.
Znalazłem dobre miejsce.
Go into those woods!
Wbiegnij do lasu.
His control center leaves something to be desired.
Jego centrum kontroli ma słabe strony.
His bodily movements lack coordination.
Jego ciało nie jest do końca skoordynowane.
That's why he trips and lets his tentacles collide in mid-air.
Dlatego się potyka i zaplątują mu się macki.
why do you think his head does not morph and join in the offensive?
No i dlaczego jego głowa pozostała niezmieniona?
You're right.
Racja.
The head has its hands full coordinating the arms and other parasitic components.
Głowa jest zajęta koordynacją ramion i innych części ciała.
So, if the head were to morph, he would fall into chaos.
Gdyby głowa się przemieniła, straciłby panowanie.
There's nothing to fear.
Bez obaw.
In the end, there is only one enemy.
Ostatecznie to tylko jeden przeciwnik.
All right, we'll fight here. Stop.
Zatrzymaj się. Możemy tu walczyć.
Rather than aiming for the legs or torso, go for the head.
Nie celuj w nogi ani tors, tylko w głowę.
Decapitation is the most certain strategy.
Dekapitacja to najpewniejsza strategia.
But how do we…
Ale jak…?
We can do it!
Damy radę.
At my signal, make a beeline for him at top speed!
Biegnij na niego na mój sygnał.
-What? -Trust me.
- Co? - Zaufaj mi.
I finally caught up with you guys.
Wreszcie was dogoniłem.
Don't move!
Nie ruszaj się.
Using the trees as a shield,
Używaj drzew jako osłony.
dodge his attacks by moving right and left and up and down
Unikaj jego ataków i utrzymuj stały dystans.
If we continue to evade by moving in a straight line,
Jeśli będziemy poruszać się w prostej linii,
and predict our next move.
spróbuje przewidzieć nas następny ruch.
That's when we spring our surprise.
Wtedy go zaskoczymy.
Now!
Teraz!
From his perspective, the hunted, moving in a straight line,
Zwierzyna poruszająca się w prostej linii
is now suddenly the hunter, rushing toward him as a point.
nagle zmieni się w drapieżnika.
What was parallel will have become perpendicular,
Równoległa linia ruchu zmieni się w prostopadłą.
To someone who already struggles to utilize his striking tentacles,
Zmaga się z kontrolowaniem macek,
he won't gain his bearings in time to attack us.
więc nie zdoła nas zaatakować.
We did it!
Udało się!
-What's wrong? -You can…
- Co jest? - Czy to możliwe?
Time to swap leads.
Czas na zmianę.
Come back, Miki.
Wracaj, Miki.
Well, this is embarrassing.
Co za wstyd.
That goes without saying.
Owszem.
You should stay a right hand, Miki.
Zostań w prawej ręce, Miki.
It wasn't three of them.
Nie było ich trzech.
-What? -Look.
- Co? - Spójrz.
He is now completely one.
Teraz stanowi całość.
In an instant, he assumed control over his entire body
Przejął kontrolę nad całym ciałem
and became a single lifeform.
i stał się jedną istotą.
However, before that happened, their consciousness split into five.
Ale wcześniej ich świadomość podzieliła się na pięć części.
In other words, there are five total parasites on that body!
A więc to ciało skrywa pięć pasożytów.
Five?
Pięć?
When the other one was the "head",
Kiedy poprzedni zajmował głowę,
I felt there were three
wyczułem trzy,
because he was unable to unify them into one.
bo nie był w stanie ich zjednoczyć.
You are correct.
Zgadza się.
Only Miki and I can serve as the control
Tylko Miki i ja możemy sprawować kontrolę,
and only I can unify everyone.
ale tylko ja mogę wszystkich zjednoczyć.
Migi.
Migi.
Yeah, now is not the time to gawk in awe.
To naprawdę imponujące.
It appears we have traveled quite a ways while I was asleep.
Wygląda na to, że przebyliśmy niezły kawał, kiedy spałem.
I've seen you before.
Już cię widziałem.
You're…
Ty…
His movements are totally different now!
Porusza się zupełnie inaczej.
Not even monkeys can move like that!
Nawet małpy nie są tak zwinne.
Being in the woods is now working to our disadvantage!
Drzewa działają teraz na naszą niekorzyść.
He's quite fast for a human.
Jest szybki jak na człowieka.
Excuse me!
Przepraszam!
Shit.
Szlag!
We're getting on.
Wsiadamy.
-Shit! -No way!
O kurde! Niemożliwe.
He's even capable of that?
To on tak potrafi?
What the…
Co jest?
I… I'm going 60 kph.
Jadę 60 kilometrów na godzinę.
Is that a monster?
Co to za potwór?
Migi.
Migi!
It's not my fault.
To nie moja wina.
I had no part in this!
Ja nic nie zrobiłem.
That douchebag drove off!
Co za drań. Zostawił go tu.
Hey, are you okay?
Żyjesz?
I feel lethargic.
Czuję się osłabiony.
It must be from the blood loss earlier. I don't have enough blood.
Musiałem stracić za dużo krwi.
Blood?
Krwi?
&lrm;FUKUYAMA POLICE STATION
POLICJA
I understand your pain.
Rozumiem, co pan czuje,
-But-- -Is there anyone called Hirama-san here?
- ale… - Jest tu niejaki Hirama?
Hirama?
Hirama?
-Chief. -You may go.
- Panie komendancie. - Możecie odejść.
Kuramori-san,
Kuramori-san,
I won't ask you why you know about Inspector Hirama.
nie spytam, skąd zna pan inspektora Hiramę.
You must have some idea about the parasites.
Musi pan coś wiedzieć o pasożytach.
Shinichi, buy some clothes.
Shinichi, kup nowe ubranie.
We stand out too much.
Rzucamy się w oczy.
Then we'll need to eat.
I musimy coś zjeść.
Sure, but I don't have money.
Nie mam pieniędzy.
What?
Co?
Where did you get that money?
Skąd je wziąłeś?
From the truck earlier.
Od tamtego kierowcy.
But I am not human,
Nie jestem człowiekiem,
so don't bring up human laws and morals.
więc nie pouczaj mnie o ludzkich prawach.
But you're my hand, aren't you?
Ale jesteś moją ręką.
This is what I did in order to preserve my life.
Zrobiłem, co musiałem, w trosce o swoje życie.
I am a different species from you,
Pochodzimy z różnych gatunków,
but we are in a partnership,
ale jesteśmy partnerami,
which demands mutual respect.
więc musimy się szanować.
On that premise, the common purpose that binds us
Łączy nas jeden cel:
is survival.
przetrwanie.
But isn't that theft?
Ale to była kradzież.
Sure.
Owszem.
Moving on,
Pozostałe wiadomości. Żona i najstarsza córka Kuramori-sana
were killed by a sharp
zginęły od ran ciętych…
-sword-like weapon. -Kuramori? Can it be?
Kuramori? Czy to możliwe?
Furthermore, Kuramori-san's office, which handled private investigations,
Tej samej nocy spłonęła agencja detektywistyczna Kuramori-sana.
The police intend to question Kuramori-san…
Policja zamierza przesłuchać…
They must've decided that he's too dangerous to keep alive.
Nie mogli zostawić go przy życiu.
His family was probably just collateral damage
Jego rodzina była zapewne tylko stratą uboczną.
I have to call Dad.
Muszę zadzwonić do taty.
Shinichi?
Shinichi?
Where are you, out so late?
Gdzie jesteś? Późno już.
Dad, listen closely.
Tato, posłuchaj.
Please get out of the house right now.
Proszę, wyjdź natychmiast z domu.
What's happened, Shinichi?
Co się stało?
A lot of things.
Wiele rzeczy. Nie mogę na razie wrócić do domu.
Why? Tell me everything from the beginning!
Dlaczego? Powiedz mi wszystko!
Everything?
Wszystko?
There's no way I can tell him everything!
Nie mogę powiedzieć mu wszystkiego.
But I have to hurry.
Muszę się spieszyć.
If I don't…
Inaczej…
Dad, I…
Tato…
I've been a good son in general, right? I never really acted out.
byłem dobrym synem, prawda? Nie robiłem ci kłopotów.
I think I'm still a good son, even after Mom died,
Myślę, że wciąż nim jestem, choć mama umarła i zostaliśmy sami.
So, I'm not trying to mess around right now, either.
Nie chcę robić ci trudności.
So, please, Dad.
Ale proszę, tato,
Please leave the house right now!
natychmiast wyjdź z domu.
A monster is coming!
Zbliża się potwór.
It's the one that killed Mom!
Ten, który zabił mamę!
And you're safe?
A ty jesteś bezpieczny?
Yes.
Tak.
All right.
W porządku.
I'll leave.
Wyjdę.
I trust you.
Ufam ci.
Thank you, Dad.
Dziękuję, tato.
I am Hirama.
Nazywam się Hirama.
My sincere condolences for your wife and child.
Moje kondolencje z powodu śmierci żony i dziecka.
Their bodies are still being examined by the M.E.,
Wciąż trwa sekcja zwłok,
but I believe what I saw confirms my beliefs.
ale zdaje się, że moje podejrzenia były słuszne.
Please tell me what you think.
Co pan myśli?
Kuramori-san, let's avenge their deaths!
Pomścijmy ich śmierć!
-Avenge? -Yes!
- Pomścijmy? - Tak.
Ever since I was a little boy,
Już od dzieciństwa
I had a deep admiration for great detectives,
podziwiałem detektywów…
like Sherlock Holmes,
takich jak Sherlock Holmes.
and after many things happened,
W końcu udało mi się zostać jednym z nich, ale…
Hey, listen.
Proszę posłuchać.
You can still become a great detective.
Wciąż może być pan wielkim detektywem.
Will I be able to avenge them?
Czy zdołam ich pomścić?
Of course!
Oczywiście.
I… I have some information.
Mam pewne informacje.
But my thoughts are all jumbled together.
Ale mam mętlik w głowie.
Can I get something to write with and somewhere I can calm down?
Mogę dostać coś do pisania i pójść w jakieś spokojniejsze miejsce?
Of course.
Oczywiście.
No, this isn't telepathy.
Nie, to nie telepatia.
But how many times has it been?
Ale który to już raz?
It's our 16th time meeting in your dreams,
To nasze szesnaste spotkanie w twoim śnie,
though you'll forget all about it again.
ale o tym również zapomnisz.
But you look nothing like the Migi I know in reality.
Nie wyglądasz jak Migi, którego znam.
You say the same thing every time.
Zawsze mówisz to samo.
You don't look anything like the Shinichi I know in reality, either.
A ty nie wyglądasz jak Shinichi, którego znam ja.
What? Leaving already?
Już odchodzisz?
I have learned that there is no way for me to communicate with the 30%
Nie potrafię skomunikować się z 30 procentami komórek,
of my cells that have dissipated into your body.
które rozeszły się po twoim ciele.
There is no further point in our meeting like this in your dreams.
Dalsze spotkania we śnie nie mają sensu.
Besides, we really don't have much time to lose back in reality.
Poza tym nie mamy czasu do stracenia.
We don't?
Nie?
You'll remember once you wake up.
Przypomnisz sobie po obudzeniu.
Migi.
Migi.
Huh? What was I about to say?
Co chciałeś powiedzieć?
Failure on both fronts?
Porażka na obu frontach? To niedopuszczalne.
It was failure on my part to let you handle dealing with the P.I.
Niepotrzebnie zleciłam wam zabójstwo detektywa.
Killing his family without killing him?
Zabiliście jego rodzinę zamiast jego?
You are ignorant of human nature.
Nie znacie ludzkiej natury.
The room was dark.
W pokoju było ciemno.
Don't we just need to kill him next?
Zabijemy go w następnej kolejności.
You all underestimate humans.
Nie doceniacie ludzi.
Individually, they may appear weak, but that is not the case.
W pojedynkę wydają się słabi, ale to mylny osąd.
What we need to recognize
Musimy zrozumieć,
is that humans are a single lifeform comprised of millions of individuals.
że ludzie to jeden organizm złożony z milionów istot.
Besides their individual brains,
Poza indywidualnymi mózgami
humans possess a different "brain" of enormous magnitude.
ludzie posiadają umysł o wielkiej skali.
The moment we act in opposition to that brain,
Jeśli będziemy działać wbrew temu umysłowi, przegramy.
Lose?
Przegramy?
Are you truly one of us?
Na pewno jesteś jedną z nas?
Something is different.
Coś się zmieniło.
Something…
Coś…
Izumi-kun didn't even show up to school today.
Izumi-kun nie pojawił się w szkole.
He was acting like something really bad was going on yesterday, too.
Wczoraj zachowywał się, jakby stało się coś złego.
Satomi.
Satomi.
Here, take this.
Proszę.
It's the bag Izumi-kun left behind.
Izumi-kun zostawił ten plecak.
You should go take it to him.
Daj mu go.
Huh? But…
Ale…
It'll be a chance to patch things up, too.
Będziecie mieli okazję pogadać.
If you won't go, I will!
Idź, bo sama pójdę.
Kuramori-san.
Kuramori-san.
We've been had.
Przechytrzył nas.
But he's not a suspect.
Ale on nie był podejrzanym. Dlaczego uciekł?
KURAMORI
KURAMORI
Tamura Reiko.
Tamura Reiko.
A "partner"?
„Partner”?
Youko, Yumi.
Youko, Yumi. Własnoręcznie pomszczę waszą śmierć.
Tamura Reiko!
Tamura Reiko!
Tamura Reiko.
Tamura Reiko.
No, she is not one of us!
Nie, nie jest jedną z nas.
She's dangerous.
Jest niebezpieczna.
She's a threat to our kind!
Zagraża naszemu gatunkowi.
How mysterious.
Ciekawe.
You are a mystery.
Jesteś dla mnie zagadką.
This world is full of mystery.
Ten świat jest pełen tajemnic.
Why was I…
Dlaczego…
Why were we born?
Dlaczego się rodzimy?
Like I thought, he's not home.
Nie ma go w domu.
Where are you?
Gdzie ty jesteś?
Hey, are you safe,
Jesteś bezpieczny?
Izumi-kun?
Izumi-kun.
Tamura Reiko, it was you.
Tamura Reiko, to byłaś ty.
You're the one who dragged me into this hell.
To ty wciągnęłaś mnie w to piekło.
Three of them?
Trójka?
Their intent seems less than peaceful.
Nie mają pokojowych zamiarów.
Where is she going?
Dokąd ona idzie?
No matter.
Nieważne.
While I still have time.
Wykorzystam okazję.
Good evening, Tamura-san.
Dobry wieczór, Tamura-san.
It seems it's more difficult to conceal than I'd thought.
Zamaskowanie się jest trudniejsze, niż myślałem.
Yes, the strongest signal we are capable of emanating
Zamiar zabójstwa to najsilniejszy sygnał, jaki możemy wysłać.
That's when we harbor animosity toward another, after all.
W końcu to wtedy emanujemy wrogością.
Next time, "The Adventure of the Dying Detective."
Następny odcinek: „Przygoda umierającego detektywa”